Get started now. Today is דף ט׳ *Daf Tes*. We pick up
at the bottom of ע"ט עמוד ב' *Ayin Tes Amud Beis*. תניא
*Tanya*, right? Is that where we're up to? תניא *Tanya*. Okay, so
we're dealing now with the minimum amount of eating and drinking on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*. And we have, we're focusing on
the כותבת kotevet, *koseves*, the date, the dried date, the big dried
date together with its pit, and trying to figure out if it's
more or less than a ביצה beitzah, *beitzah*. Different proofs, different positions
both ways. תניא *Tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braita, *Baraisa*, רבי
אומר *Rebbi Omer*: כל השיעורים בכולתן כזית kezayit, *Kol hashiurim bekuleitan kekizayis*.
All the שיעורים shiurim. *shiurim* are with a כזית kezayit. *kezayis*, meaning
the vast majority of
שיעורים shiurim, *shiurim* in, you know, when we in, in הלכה halacha
*Halacha* are a כזית kezayit, *kezayis*, חוץ מטומאת אוכלין *chutz mitumas ochalin*,
except for impurity of foods, ששינה הכתוב במשמען ושינו חכמים בשיעורן *sheshina
kasuv bemasma'an veshinu chachamim bishiuran*, that the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk* uses a
slightly different term when it talks about foods becoming טמא tamei *tamei*
and therefore the חכמים *Chachamim* defined a different amount and not a
כזית kezayit *kezayis*. וראיה לדבר יום הכפורים *Vera'aya ledavar Yom Hakippurim*, and
if you want an example of something that is a, that is
not a כזית kezayit, *kezayis* because of a different use of a
word in the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*, look at יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
*Yom Kippur*. יום כיפור Yom Kippur? *Yom Kippur* the Torah doesn't say
don't eat, it says you shall afflict yourself. And because it uses
a different term that means it's conceptualizing it differently. It's not about
eating, it's about afflicting and therefore as we saw the amount isn't
a כזית kezayit *kezayis*, it's a כותבת kotevet. *koseves*. So, מאי שינה
הכתוב במשמעו *mai shina kasuv bemasma'o*? Where did the Torah use a,
you know, change its meaning in the case of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *Yom Kippur*? מלו תעונה *milo te'uneh*, it says any soul that
does not afflict itself. So therefore it's not about eating, it's about
afflicting. ומאי שינו חכמים בשיעורי *umai shinu chachamim bishiurei*, and where did
the חכמים *Chachamim* say that therefore that led to a different size?
ככותבת kekosaves, *kekoseves*, a כותבת *koseves*, not a כזית kezayit *kezayis*. ומאי
ראיה לדבר יום הכפורים *Umai ra'aya ledavar Yom Hakippurim*? Meaning okay, that's
a good example. But why did you say, why didn't you just
say look, by the טומאה tumah *tumah* of foodstuff, different word, which
we'll see in a minute what that different word is or different
phrase, and therefore a different size? And by analogy the same is
true by יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*. But why are we
being a proof from יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*? What makes
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* a more evident example of this
idea than the issue we're dealing with at hand, which is the
point of טומאה tumah. *tumah* foodstuff? Just say in both of them
the פסוקים pesukim, *Psukim* used a different phrase and we come up
with a different size. So here's why we want יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *Yom Kippur* to be our paradigm. It says, דאי מהתם *de'ee
mei'hasam*, had you just had the case by food, by טומאה *tumah*
food, הוה אמינא דיכרא הוא *hava amina dichrahu*, I would have said
you know, it's not a real change, it's not a real difference
of the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk*, that's just the way the פסוק pasuk
*Pasuk* talks, not a big difference. Okay, טומאת אוכלין *tumas ochalin*...
so now, and now we're going to see why is that indication.
So therefore the point being though, יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*
is a good model that when the Torah uses phrases something differently
it leads to a different שיעור shiur, *shiur*. Because there it's very
clearly different word. It's not don't eat, it's afflict yourself. That clearly
is a very distinct
word and concept. So you can't just say like a type of
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*, דברה תורה torah כלשון בני אדם *dibrah Torah
keleshon bnei adam*, 'Oh making a big deal out of nothing'. Making
a big deal out of nothing, it doesn't say don't eat, it
says afflict yourself, conceptually that's different. So if by יום כיפור Yom
Kippur *Yom Kippur* you see that that difference leads to a different
size, then by other things too, even when the difference is more
subtle, we've already established the precedent that that can lead to a
different size.
Not the same size though. No, no, no.
Now let's take a look by the טומאה *tumah* foodstuff. Okay, now,
טומאת אוכלין
כביצה kabeitza. מנלן *tumas ochalin kibeitzah minalan*? Now the טומאה *tumah* of
foods is a minimum size is a כביצה kebeitza. *kibeitzah*. There's a
whole question does that in order to become טמא tamei. *tamei*, in
order to pass on the טומאה *tumah*? We won't worry about that
right now, but it's a כביצה *kibeitzah*. Where do you get that
from? Now let's look at that actual point that's being made. אמר
רב אבהו אמר רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar. *amar Rav Avahu amar Rabbi
Elazar* דאמר קרא *de'amar kra*, the verse says: מכל האכל אשר יאכל
*mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel*. Okay, it says אשר יבא *asher yavo*, what
is it? מכל האכל אשר יאכל אשר יבא עליו מים יטמא *mikol
ha'ochel asher ye'achel asher yavo elav mayim yitma*. From all the food
that shall be eaten, so אשר יאכל *asher ye'achel*, food that shall
be eaten, like just say food. Okay, so there you see it's
not a huge difference like by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* it says
fast as opposed to don't eat. But still there's something different about
this פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk*, food that will be eaten. So what does
that mean? So that's coming to tell you a different size. אוכל
הבא מחמת אוכל *ochel haba meichamas ochel*. אוכל *ochel* from אשר יאכל
*asher ye'achel*, from something that is eaten. So food that comes from
food. ואיזה *Ve'eizeh*? What is food that comes from food? זה ביצת
תרנגולת tarnegoret. *zeh beitzas tarnigoles*, an egg of a chicken. A chicken
is food, an egg comes from it, so it's a food from
food and that's what the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* is talking about. So
now you see why that's a bit more of a stretch than
לא תעונה *lo te'uneh* by יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. But okay, that's
a hint already that we should be looking at a different size.
ואימא ve'eima גדי *Ve'eima gidi*? I don't get it, there's other food
that comes from food, you know, how about a, you know, how
about a what do you call... how about a goat? How about
a kid? How about milk? Okay, so the גמרא gemara says right,
that's why milk should be פליישיג fleishig because it comes from a
cow. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says מחוסר שחיטה mechusar shechita because
no, that's not food when it's born, you still have to שחט
shecht it. So it's not like an egg that's food the moment
it's
born. ואימא ve'eima בן פקועה? ben pakua? How about... how about an
animal, it's so funny when the גמרא gemara brings in בן פקועה.
ben pakua. So you שחט... shecht... you שחט shechted an animal and
then you found in it a... it was... it was pregnant and
there was a fetus of an unborn you know calf inside of
the cow that you שחט. shechted. Fully formed. So because you did
a שחיטה shechita on the mother while the calf was in utero,
the שחיטה shechita takes effect on the calf, and this calf now
does not need שחיטה shechita even though it's walking around and alive.
So the גמרא gemara says that would be a case where it
was food from food, it was born as it were, came out
of the mother's womb after you שחט shechted the mother, and that's
ראוי ra'uy to be eaten immediately, it doesn't need שחיטה. shechita. All
right, so that's a pretty bizarre case. So the גמרא gemara says
טעון קריעה. te'un keria. No, you might not need to שחט shecht
it, but you still need to tear it and to get the
blood out. There's still a blood problem.
I'm sorry, did the גמרא gemara find say?
Says that's what the תורה Torah says. Yeah, so maybe the... maybe
it's a huge amount, maybe it's the size of a... of a
goat that's born out of utero, that's taken out of utero. Okay,
instead of an egg,
and they're all often different sizes,
big goats and small goats. All right, so anyway, well the גמרא's
gemara going to get to that point. All right, anyway, just having
fun. Okay, so anyway, so it can't be that because that still
you need to you know to dismember it and get out the
blood. So the גמרא gemara says fine, it's an egg. But ואימא
ve'eima ביצת בר יוכני? beitzat bar yokhni?
Maybe it's an ostrich egg? Okay, so that's huge, how do you
know it's a chicken egg? So the גמרא gemara says all right,
or hen egg, תפסת מרובה לא תפסת. tafasta meruba lo tafasta.
No, you know, if you try to grab too much then you
don't come away with anything. Don't be a חזיר, chazir, you'll have
to give it all back. So anyway, so it's like... it's like
you know when they're passing around the plate at dinner and you
take too much on your plate and someone says, why don't you
put some of that back, there's other people at the table? So
okay, that's תפסת מרובה לא תפסת. tafasta meruba lo tafasta. So which
means... yeah... yeah, it means if you have can have a large
size and a small size, you don't, you know, and you try
to assert the big one, you're reaching too far, you can't make
that assumption, you have to and basically you know if you want
to frame it in another way is what allows you to be
that מקל? meikel? To say that food you know isn't a problem
of the tuma food stuff until it's the size of an ostrich
egg? You have, you know, it's an egg, so we have to
pick a normal sized egg.
So what's intended in this context, in this context context, don't be
ridiculous.
No, that don't be ridiculous
is too... is too general. It's... it's don't be a חזיר. chazer.
It's... the חזיר's chazer not appropriate here because it's not about like
desire and potch, but you know, but it is specifically meant in
the context that you cannot assume a too large of an amount
because... because you know what, if you say ostrich egg you're saying
don't be ridiculous. But let's say I tell you maybe an egg
one size up from a hen egg. How do you know? You
know there's a million types of eggs out there? How do you
know to pick the hen egg?
The jumbo egg? You know?
Yeah, exactly. Why
not go the other way? How about a sparrow? So that's the
next question. So ואימא ביצת ציפורתא? beitzat tziporta? Maybe it's the egg
of a sparrow, I think ציפורתא tziporta is sparrow? Actually it never
occurred to me, sparrow and ציפור tzipor are like the exact same
letters. Sparrow, ציפור? tzipor? Anyway, is that how they translate ציפורתא, tziporta,
sparrow? Small bird, yeah. Okay anyway, but I assume it's just like
something like a sparrow. דזוטר טובי, dizuta tuvei, that's very small. So
you want to say fine, like be מחמיר machmir or take you
know or you know don't take a size that's too big, so
there are smaller eggs. So we don't have an answer to that,
you're right, that's a good question. Now of course you could say
like the most common egg is a... is a hen egg,
but nevertheless the גמרא gemara says that's you know we're sort of
left with a question. So רבי אבהו דיאמר, Rabbi Abbahu de'amar, so
that was רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu quoting רבי אלעזר. So that has
a little bit of a problem with it, that approach, אוכל הבא
מאוכל. ochel haba mi'ochel. So רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu has another... has
his own approach to say how we know the size of a
chicken
egg. מכל האוכל אשר יאכל, Mikol ha'ochel asher ye'achel, all food that
will be eaten, there's even maybe an easier דרשה drasha closer to
the words of the
פסוק, אוכל שאתה אוכלו בבת אחת, ochel she'atah ochlo be'vat achat, food
that you eat in one gulp. So an amount of food that's
possible to be eaten in one gulp. ושיערו חכמים אין בית הבליעה
מחזיק יותר מביצת תרנגולת, Ve'shiru chakhamim ein beit hablia machzik yoter mi'beitzat
tarnegoret, and
the rabbis estimated that the size of your gullet cannot contain of
your esophagus cannot contain more than an egg, an egg of a
תרנגולת. So Natan Slifkin was here the other day, he wrote a
whole... no actually he wrote a whole big article on a כזית,
kezayis. not on a כביצה. But I know, you know, of course
there's also I don't know, I there are people, don't they have
like these egg swallowing contests and whatever? Yeah, there are people that
can swallow that can swallow eggs, to me, I don't know, it
looks way too big for me to swallow, but okay.
All right, all right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so that's how we get the idea and now you see the
point. Food that will be eaten is not a huge change in
the language of the פסוק. But since we've set a precedent from
יום כיפור that a change in terminology is a change in amount,
so, and there's a real difference, fasting versus not eating, or afflicting
versus not eating, here also that signals a different amount.
Yes. Mentioned people that could fit like a lot in their mouth.
But like I believe in גמרא מכות Gemara Makkot it says we
don't rely on like someone that has really good eyesight and... Right.
Is that always a principle in גמרא Gemara operating? Yeah.
Like just earlier
they said we go by a regular egg, we go by a
regular...
Right. The גמרא Gemara never said we go by a regular egg.
That was sort of the answer that was being that was being...
Yeah, that should have been said. But yeah, I mean, it does
sound like it's assuming like most people if they if they, you
know, if they make an effort, could get an egg into their
throat. I don't know how big their chicken eggs were. So I
don't know the answer, but to me that sounds
smaller than ours.
That's what I would guess, but people were smaller too. So I
don't know what to say. Okay, it's true. אמר רב אלעזר. Amar
Rav Elazar. Okay. האוכל חלב. ha'ocheil cheilev. Now that we're talking about
sizes and eating, we have a very fascinating next little point. Let's
take a look.
We're done, so that we just proved in the
end that the גמרא Gemara is consistent. Yeah, that's the... that's the
דרשה, drasha, at least according to רבי אבהו. Rabbi Abbahu. אמר רב
אלעזר. Amar Rav Elazar. האוכל חלב בזמן הזה, ha'ocheil cheilev bazman hazeh,
if somebody
eats forbidden fat, specifically forbidden fat, because, you know, the most standard
non-kosher foods, right, which is like חזיר chazir or an animal that's
not שחט-ed shecht properly, is only a לאו, lav, it's a negative
prohibition, it is not an איסור כרת. issur kares. And we want
to talk about things that you would get כרת kares for, because
that means that if you did it בשוגג, beshogeg, unintentionally, you would
bring a קרבן. korban. So those things would be fat... I mean,
they would come from a normal animal, but more because you did
not remove things. You didn't remove the fat and you didn't remove
the blood. Blood and fat are the two most common ways to
get כרת kares for eating non-kosher food. The other way would be
חמץ בפסח. chametz bePesach. Okay. So האוכל חלב. ha'ocheil cheilev. What? Even
בשר בחלב basar bechalav would only be a לאו, lav, would not
be
כרת. kares. האוכל חלב בזמן הזה. ha'ocheil cheilev bazman hazeh. So somebody
eats חלב cheilev nowadays. צריך שיכתוב לו שיעור. tzarich sheyichtov lo shiur.
You have to write the amount. I ate 2.3 grams of חלב.
cheilev. Or actually it goes by volume. So I ate one cubic
centimeter of חלב. cheilev. שמא יבוא בית דין אחר. shema yavo beis
din acher. Maybe in later another בית דין beis din court will
come וירבו בשיעורין veyarbe bishiurin and they'll increase the sizes. Now, and
meaning you want to know, you want to have a record, so
when the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is built, you're able to bring
all the קרבנות korbanos that you were חייב. chayav. Just because there's
no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash now doesn't mean you're not חייב chayav
in a קרבן. korban. Okay. So God willing, you should merit and
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash should be built in your lifetime and
you should bring all the קרבנות korbanos that you've been חייב chayav
so far. So you need to keep a record. So don't just
write down in your little פנקס, pinkas, in your little notebook, right,
you know the stories of like, you know, the צדיקים tzaddikim that
would like carry little notebooks, you know, write down every tiny little
thing that they would do so they could do תשובה teshuva for.
So here though, the גמרא's Gemara like taking for granted that you
have a little notebook in which you're writing down the קרבנות korbanos
you're חייב chayav for, which by the way is fascinating. Again, thinking
about the larger theme of our מסכת masechet with, you know, sort
of what I've been trying to bring out and underline, sort of
tension if you will or, you know, competing themes about קרבן korban
as what you do for sins as opposed to like תשובה teshuva
is what you do for sins. Okay, but so here it's mentioning,
oh, you know, you ate חלב? cheilev? Write down in your notebook
that you're חייב chayav a קרבן. korban. Okay. But don't just write
down I'm חייב chayav a קרבן, korban, even if you think you
ate a כזית. kezayis, Write down I ate, you know, 2.3 cubic
centimeters. Why? A later בית דין beis din will come and they'll
change the minimum amounts and they'll change the minimum amounts and maybe
you won't be חייב chayav a קרבן korban or maybe you thought
you were and you won't, maybe you thought you weren't and you
will. Now, whatever happened about grandfathering you in? You know? Shouldn't it
be defined by how the הלכה halacha was defined at the time
you ate it? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about
this.
Wait, I love it. But it's very beautiful as you just said.
In other words, this anticipation of the ability to bring a קרבן
korban in terms of מקדש, Mikdash, but the act of writing in
the notebook with scales on both sides of תשובה. teshuva. That's interesting.
The writing is simultaneously
the anticipation for the future, but you're embedded in a תשובה teshuva
process by writing.
Oh, I didn't even connect those two, but that's interesting. But I
don't know if that's anachronistic, meaning we talk about the writing in
the notebook as a תשובה teshuva process, but that's an interesting point.
Okay, if we can if we can ignore the anachronism and then
we can literally bring those two realities together, very nice. Okay. Thank
you for bringing to the surface what was under the surface, what
was subtextual that I wasn't even thinking about. Okay. So the גמרא
Gemara says like
this. Okay. אי נימא דירבה בשיעורין, ei neima d'yarbe bishiurin, what does
it mean they'll increase the sizes? אי נימא דמחייבי קרבן אכזית קטן.
ei neima demichayevei korban akeisayis katan. Now, this is an interesting interpretation
of the word increase, but the גמרא Gemara will ask about this,
but what they're saying is let's say you mean that they'll say
that the minimum size is less, that they'll say that even a
small, you know, olive... I mean, how big of an olive? Average
olive, big olive, you know, A, double-A size? So... Okay, so here
I was just at the supermarket the other day. No, I was
at the supermarket the other day, and I said to the store
manager, what is the difference between grade AA eggs and grade AAA
eggs? He said, I have no idea.
Okay, but I guess we should say no, we should say large,
extra-large, or jumbo, right? That's the sizes of eggs. Anyway, if they
say that you're חייב chayav a קרבן korban even on a small
כזית, kezayis, so you thought you would be off the hook and
later on you'll find out that no, actually now we're redefining the
sizes and even that small amount is a small כזית kezayis? and
you're חייב. chayav. והתניא אשר לא תעשינה בשגגה די ה, Ve-hatanya Asher
lo te'asina bishgaga dei-ha-Shem, if somebody does a sin which should not
be done and he does it inadvertently
and he sins, so we make the דרשה derasha as the following.
אשר לא תעשינה, Asher lo te'asina, it's a sin that had you
known about it you wouldn't have done
it. השב מידיעתו מביא קרבן על שגגתו, ha-shav mi-ye-di-ato meivi korban al
shigagato, a person who brings a קרבן korban is somebody that would
have refrained from doing it had they been aware. לא שב מידיעתו,
Lo shav mi-ye-di-ato, if you would not have refrained even had you
been aware, אין מביא קרבן על שגגתו. ein meivi korban al shigagato.
You don't bring a קרבן. korban. So here,
if it's an amount that when you were doing it was below
the minimum size, then you wouldn't bring a קרבן korban because you
would not have refrained. Now that's a very bizarre way of phrasing
it. What do you mean of course you would have refrained? Didn't
we just have a discussion at the beginning of the פרק perek
that חצי שיעור chatzi shiur is a biblical concern? I would have
refrained. It's not the point that I wouldn't have refrained. So again,
I don't know exactly how to sit it into the words, but
I think what the גמרא Gemara is really saying is aren't you
grandfathered in? At the time you did the sin it wasn't חייב
chayav a קרבן. korban. So therefore, since it's defined by the nature
of the act at the time it was done, and at the
time it was done you were not doing something that was defined
as an act of אכילה, achila, it was at that time it
was defined as less than כזית, kezayis so therefore you should not
be obligated in a קרבן korban later on. So you cannot say
בית דין beis din will shrink the sizes and retrospectively you'll be
חייב. chayav. גמרא Gemara says fine, we meant the other way. אלא
דלא מחייבי קרבן עד דכזית גדול, Ela de-lo mechayvei korban ad dekazayit
gadol, you will think you're חייב chayav a קרבן korban and then
because you ate something the size of a כזית kezayis and then
a later בית דין beis din will come and they'll say, oh
no, you don't have to bring a קרבן korban unless it was
a bigger amount. So then you get off the hook. Right? So
that's actually interesting because when people speak about being grandfathered in, they
only want to be grandfathered in on the things that are for
their benefit. They want to be entitled to all the new rules
that help
them. So now we've got a new minimum size, it's larger, so
actually you're off the hook, which makes sense because you could say
even though I was חייב chayav קרבן korban then, I'm not going
to be allowed to bring a קרבן korban now if it's for
the sake of something that is no longer חייב chayav a קרבן.
korban.
No,
that's but I say you don't speak about being grandfathered in for
the bad, you speak about grandfathered in for the good. So I
can't be bringing a קרבן korban for something that is not right
now sufficient to be מחייב mechayev a קרבן. korban. Okay, so therefore
you should write the amount because you might not
be
חייב chayav a קרבן korban later on. גמרא Gemara says, ולמאי דסלקא
דעתך מעיקרא, u-le-mai de-salka daitech me-ikara, now what we initially thought, מחייבי
קרבן אכזית קטן, mechayvei korban akazayit katan, that the בית דין beis
din would shrink the sizes and that you might retroactively be חייב
chayav for now the new smaller size for what you did in
the past, מאי ירבה בשיעורין? mai yarbe beshiurin? What does it mean
a בית דין beis din will come and increase the sizes? They're
not increasing, you thought that it meant that they'll say that they'll
make a smaller minimum. How does that fit with the words ירבה
בשיעורין? yarbe beshiurin? So what it means is שמא ירבה בקרבנות מחמת
שיעורין. shema yarbe be-korbanos machmat shiurin. It means they'll be more מחמיר
machmir by a minimum, but being more מחמיר machmir by a minimum
means making a smaller minimum not a larger minimum. מחמיר machmir we
normally think of as more demanding, but to be מחמיר machmir by
a minimum means a smaller. So ירבה בשיעורין yarbe beshiurin means they'll
be more increasing obligations
regarding שיעורין shiurin because they'll make the שיעורין shiurin smaller. The גמרא
Gemara, wants to know
how could anyone ever have considered the possibility that it was a
smaller כזית kezayis
if
the phrase is ירבה בשיעורין? yarbe beshiurin? And it means ירבה בחיובים
yarbe bechiyuvin
regarding שיעורין. shiurin. ירבה קרבנות yarbe korbanos regarding שיעורין. shiurin. But in
the end it says you'd be grandfathered in and therefore the only
possibility is that now you'd get off the hook because we made
the minimum larger. Yes Dov?
You'd think that the difference the distinction would be between whether the
בית דין beis din was doing legislation or interpretation. If it was
legislation, then it shouldn't be retroactive. But if it's interpretation, they're
revealing
that
what you actually did was... But you ask a lot of questions
that way. That's questions like for the beginning of הוריות. Horayos. They
rule something is מותר muttar and then retroactively they say it's אסור
assur and now how do you deal like for example if a
בית דין beis din comes along and says everything, there's a thing
you've all been eating on פסח, Pesach, you've all been eating quinoa
on פסח, Pesach, we've just really realized that quinoa is a grain
and you're all חייב כרת chayav kares for all of, do you
really think everybody now has to bring korban even though it's an
interpretation issue? Right, it's how does, you know, that goes to this
question of in the role of תורה שבעל פה Torah She'baal Peh
interpreting the פסוקים, pesukim. are they discovering an absolute truth that was
always there, or is it the interpretive truth and therefore it only
sort of takes effect from this time on? So I think that
that's implied by the גמרא, Gemara although maybe not. You could say
what the גמרא Gemara is just saying since the גמרא Gemara frames
it, I tried to redefine it, but the גמרא Gemara frames it
as you're not שב מידיעתיה. shav mi-yediata. So the way the גמרא
Gemara frames it could be,
you know what, objectively you were חייב chayiv a קרבן, korban, but
this הלכה halacha depends on your psychological state of mind. That does
seem to be what the גמרא Gemara is saying because you raise
a very important question which comes up at the beginning of הוריות
Horayos as well. When בית דין Beis Din goes back and reinterprets
a biblical verse and a biblical criteria, is it rediscovering a truth
that was always true, or is it creating a new interpretive truth,
a new הלכה halacha truth based on that interpretation? Okay, so now
גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, said
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, שיעורין ועונשין הלכה למשה מסיני. shiurin v'onshin halacha
l'Moshe mi-Sinai. The minimum amount of sizes and punishments are הלכה למשה
מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai.
Since he knows he's not going to change the שיעור, shiur, is
that what he's saying?
No, it's just a new point. Now that we're talking about שיעור,
shiur we're onto a new topic.
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai then they can't change it, they
can't say it's now...
Oh, that's a good point, but I guess, you know,
I didn't read it that way. You're right, you could read it
that he's saying this isn't even possible because it's all, it's all
tradition, it's all fixed, but even within the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
l'Moshe mi-Sinai there could be questions like the same way there's questions
by מפורש פסוקים. mefurash pesukim. The הלכה is a כזית. kezayis Big
כזית, kezayis. small כזית, kezayis you know, exactly how do you define
the minimum size of a כזית? kezayit, גמרא Gemara didn't say you'll
switch a כזית kezayit to a כביצה. So I don't think הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai means that there's no debate. Even according
to the רמב"ם, Rambam, says there was never debate about הלכה למשה
מסיני, halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai, it doesn't mean that there can't be interpretive
questions of exactly what the scope of it is. Okay, so I
did not read it that way.
There's a little bit of fuzziness even in הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha
l'Moshe mi-Sinai.
Yeah, like anything. You can't, you know, anything, you don't know the
exact parameters.
You don't know the exact boundaries.
Right, I'm saying but there will always be questions about the exact
boundary lines and exact parameters. Okay,
אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, okay, what? Someone doesn't like fuzziness.
I know. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, שיעורין ועונשין, shiurin v'onshin,
but we're talking about שיעורין shiurin and we're talking about punishments for
minimum size, so he says it's all הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe
mi-Sinai. So the גמרא Gemara says עונשין מיכתב כתיבי. onshin michsav kesivi.
What do you mean? Punishments for עבירות aveiros are in the פסוקים.
pesukim, כרת, Kares, you know, חייב מיתה. chayiv misa. Now, of course
it's interesting because there's a lot that are not in the פסוקים,
pesukim. particularly מלקות. malkos. The assumption of who gets מלקות malkos and
to generalize it, you know, the תורה Torah mentions מלקות malkos once
or twice, besides the fact that חז"ל Chazal try to say, well,
you know, it means to do a מעשה maaseh and it can't
be לאו שאין בו מעשה, lav she'ein bo maaseh, but the very
idea that there's a generalizable category of
מלקות malkos that applies to most things, that's not in the פסוקים.
psukim, So anyway, you could have said that there's aspects of הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai there as well.
We don't even know what מות יומת mos yumas means, right?
Right, true, right. What are the ארבע מיתות arba misos and so
on. But the גמרא Gemara resists it. The גמרא Gemara says, no,
אלא הכי קאמר, ela haki ka'amar, this is what it means. שיעורין
של עונשין הלכה למשה מסיני, shiurin shel onshin halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai, the
minimum amount that's needed for punishments is הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe
mi-Sinai, which is a funny statement because we normally say all שיעורין
shiurin is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. The minimum size for
a מקוה, mikvah, the minimum size for an אתרוג, esrog, the minimum
size for a לולב, lulav, so it's not just the minimum for
עונש. onesh. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, similarly שיעורין של עונשין,
shiurin shel onshin, the minimum amount for punishments is הלכה למשה מסיני.
halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, now this will be a
shocker, בית
דינו של יעבץ תיקנום. Beis Dino shel Yavetz tiknum. It's actually no,
not from סיני, Sinai, it's the בית דין Beis Din of יעבץ.
Yavetz. Who's יעבץ? Yavetz? It was רבי יעקב עמדין. Rabbi Yaakov Emden.
No, I'm kidding because
that was יעקב עמדין בן צבי. Yaakov Emden ben Tzvi. Anyway,
right. But okay, if you take a look at the second wide
line of רש"י, Rashi, who? עתניאל בן קנז. Othniel ben Kenaz. Okay,
based on a פסוק, that's where the phrase יעבץ Yavetz comes from.
It was from the time of the שופטים Shoftim I believe. So
okay, it was his בית דין, Beis Din, although way at the
beginning of, you know, the Jewish history somewhere there in פרשת שופטים,
parshas Shoftim, not שופטים, Shoftim, no, in ספר שופטים, Sefer Shoftim, but
not from הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai.
That's about the punishments or the minimum sizes? What's the מדרש midrash
about he
renewed all the
laws?
Yeah, exactly.
Because they forgot them and they renewed them. Whole thing with יהושע
Yehoshua and עתניאל. Othniel. Exactly, exactly,
which is quite fascinating, which actually means, you know, goes to this
question about, then it would be quite interesting because חז"ל Chazal then
would be taking something that the תורה Torah didn't even, is it
going so far as to say the תורה Torah didn't even have
a concept of minimum size? That according to the תורה Torah you'd
get punished for even a speck, and חז"ל Chazal created a minimum?
Presumably not that. Presumably what it's saying is that the תורה Torah,
had a concept of a minimum, but it left it to חז"ל
Chazal to define what that minimum
was. That was done not from סיני, Sinai, that was done by
עתניאל בן קנז, Othniel ben Kenaz, that was done, you know, in
the early Joshua period, but not מסיני. mi-Sinai. Right, so the גמרא
Gemara says דהכתיב אלה המצוות שאין נביא רשאי לחדש דבר מעתה, de-hachtiv
elleh ha-mitzvot she-ein navi rasha'i le-chadesh davar mei-attah, but the גמרא Gemara
does not find a way to reconcile that. It says no, if
this is not in the תורה, Torah that would be a complete
change of the law, you know, introducing an idea of minimum sizes,
and we say that נביאים Nevi'im can't do it. אלא שכחום וחזרו
ויסדום. ella she-shachachum ve-chazaru ve-yisadum.
It must be that they were always there, but they had been
forgotten, and this is also the discussion around יעבץ Yabetz and the
famous אגדתא, Aggadeta, and he rediscovered them. By the way, that's quite
fascinating, this possibility that he was נתקין netakein and the גמרא's Gemara
resistance to take it literally is quite fascinating within the discussion of
the עינויים inuyim because I mentioned before I left that although we've
been dealing with דרשות drashot of the other עינויים, inuyim, and the
question is that it sounds like they're learning it from פסוקים, psukim
but on the other hand, there are a lot of exceptions. You
know, if you're dirty you could wash it off, if you got
itches or whatever on your scalp you could use some oil, and
not only that, that you could say is not an exception, that's
a definition. That it's only אסור assur to bathe or to use
oil in a way of תענוג, ta'anug, not when it's being done
in a way that is to get rid of an irritation and
for some other purpose. Fine, but how about allowing the king to
wash his face and the כלה kallah to wash her face? That's
not saying it's a different type of washing, that's saying we're going
to allow it because of a special reason, because some other concern
is pushing us, trumping it. So how would you do that on
דאורייתא? d'oraita? So based on that, רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and many
ראשונים Rishonim say clearly the other עינויים inuyim are rabbinic. If we're
going to allow the כלה kallah and the king to wash their
face, clearly it's דרבנן d'rabbanan and therefore we can allow it. And
other ראשונים Rishonim say no, the תורה Torah gives a very—basically the
phrase is למוסרה הכתוב אלא לחכמים. le-mosra ha-katuv ela le-chakhamim. The תורה
Torah says, you know, indicates that there should be other עינויים inuyim
on יום כיפור, and it basically says to the rabbis, you guys
define the terms. So much that you can even define that it
doesn't apply when a woman just got married, and it doesn't apply
to a king even though it's the same type of act, you
guys completely define the terms, but ultimately this is a תורה idea
of other עינויים inuyim and you'll work out and define those parameters.
So that's, you know, that idea by the way, it's rare that
that the ראשונים, Rishonim, you know, you could say that's what happens
a lot by תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-ba'al peh, we define the
parameters, but usually it's assumed not to give as much of a
blank check and certainly not with a sense of overrides, you know,
working out the specifics but in an interpretive process, not in like
a freehand process. Anyway, the other place that's settled that that there's
a discussion exactly parallel to that is by חול המועד. Chol HaMoed.
Because by חול המועד Chol HaMoed as well, the פסוקים hint at
the idea of חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, it's not clear, it's an
אסמכתא, asmachta, is it really learning out meaning that you can't do
certain types of מלאכה? melacha? And you have something similar, it's not
you know like הפסד מרובה hefsed merubeh allows מלאכה melacha on חול
המועד. Chol HaMoed. That's another idea, something trumps. How could you trump
if it's דאורייתא? d'oraita?
Like an example like a guy gets out of jail, he was
in the jail.
Right, so a number of ראשונים Rishonim say okay, it's דרבנן d'rabbanan
and a number say no, it's דאורייתא d'oraita and use the same
phrase of למוסרה אלא לחכמים, le-mosra ela le-chakhamim, which is again more
than normal תורה שבעל פה Torah she-ba'al peh which is interpretive and
definitional, this gives you much more of a free hand to define
it and allows even for exceptions. So it's interesting talking about that
in the context of the גמרא Gemara resisting the idea that עתניאל
בן קנז Othniel ben Kenaz established the שיעורים. shiurim? Why can't you
say למוסרה הכתוב אלא לחכמים, le-mosra ha-katuv ela le-chakhamim, you know? So
it's interesting when the גמרא Gemara is prepared to say that and
not prepared to say that. Yeah, first stand.
Do you think it would make more sense for עתניאל Othniel to
נתקין netakein the minimum שיעור shiur because he's in ישראל? Israel?
Right, it was מנחל-מנחל, manhal-manhal, exactly right. True, but a lot of
this that we're reading the בבלי, Bavli, but you know a lot
of these statements like רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan statement about הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai is in ישראל Israel too, you know, so
a lot of and certainly all the Tannaitic stuff is coming from
ישראל. Israel.
Yeah, but I still don't fully grasp. What is the difference between
saying that something is הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai versus תורה
שבעל פה? Torah she-ba'al peh?
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai basically means it's not based on
interpreting a פסוק and it's just a מסורה, mesorah, whereas תורה שבעל
פה Torah she-ba'al peh is in the context of interpreting and and
according to the רמב״ם, Rambam, it's specifically is not that the that
the content was handed down, but that we used our
interpretive skills to derive the content as opposed to הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai which is the passing down of content, not in
the and it's not connected to a פסוק. Okay, אמר רב יהודה
amar Rav Yehuda and the רמב״ם Rambam claims that there was never
a מחלוקת machloket about that, but the evidence is against that. Okay,
השותה מלא לוגמיו, ha-shoteh melo lugmav, if you drink the fill of
your cheeks, that's the minimum amount.
כדי שיחזירו לצד אחד? k'dei she-yachziro le-tzad echad? Yeah.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, לא מלא
לוגמיו ממש, lo melo lugmav mamash, not literally the fill of your
cheeks, presumably it would mean like both cheeks, you know, אלא כל
שאילו יסלקנו לצד אחד ויראה כמלא לוגמיו, ella kol she-illu yesalkeno le-tzad
echad ve-yeira'eh k'melo lugmav,
if you moved it all to one side and it looked like
the fill of your cheeks. Now I don't exactly fill one cheek,
yeah, I don't exactly get the terminology, meaning not literally the fill
of your cheeks, move to the side so it looks like the
fill
of... one side and one cheek puffs up. Okay, which is a
חומרא, chumra, even that is considered a minimum. והאנן תנן מלא לוגמיו,
ve-hanan tnan mlo lugmav, it says straight the fill of your cheeks.
אימא כמלא לוגמיו eima ke-mlo lugmav like the fill of your cheeks.
מיתיבי meitivi I'll ask you on this: כמה ישתה ויהא חייב kamma
yishteh ve-yehe chayav we have a ברייתא, how much would you drink
and be חייב chayav on יום כיפור? בית שמאי אומרים רביעית Beit
Shammai omrim revi'it or a רביעית, revi'it, which is even—let's see how
much it is. But it's three, three and a half ounces. We'll
see in a minute. ובית הלל אומרים מלא לוגמיו ve-Beit Hillel omrim
mlo lugmav the fill of your cheeks. רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי
אלעזר כמלא לוגמיו Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Elazar ke-mlo lugmav which
is presumably like we were interpreting מלא לוגמיו. mlo lugmav. רבי יהודה
בן בתירה אומר כדי גמיעה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer kedei gmi'ah
enough to, like, one swallow worth, swallow's worth. So anyway, so you
see it says מלא לוגמיו. mlo lugmav. So the גמרא Gemara says
מי אדיפא ממשניתן? mi adifa mi-matnitin? That's how's that a bigger proof
than our משנה? mishna? דאוקימנא כדי שיראה de-okimna kedei she-yeira'eh that we
explained מלא לוגמיו mlo lugmav meant like כמלא לוגמיו ke-mlo lugmav so
that it appears like the fill by moving it to one side?
הכא נמי כדי שיראה. hacha nami kedei she-yeira'eh. So here say the
same thing. No, גמרא Gemara says you can't do that. אי הכי
היינו רבי אליעזר? ei hachi hainu Rabbi Eliezer? But that's what רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, כמלא לוגמיו. ke-mlo lugmav. So מלא לוגמיו mlo
lugmav must mean literally the fill of your cheeks, as רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is the one who's saying like the fill of your
cheeks. גמרא Gemara says no. איכא בינייהו מלא לוגמיו דחוק. ika beinaihu
mlo lugmav dachuk.
No, the difference is is whether you are basically, you know, really
like is it life-really
really puffed up your cheek or is it just a little protruding?
Okay, but they're both saying basically one side, not both cheeks. So
the גמרא Gemara. says one minute. מתקיף לה רב הושעיא. matkif lah
Rav Hoshaia. רב הושעיא Rav Hoshaia says one minute, if you're saying
one cheek, אי הכי הוו להו בית שמאי מחומרי בית הלל. ei
hachi havu lehu Beit Shammai mi-chumrei Beit Hillel. Two cheeks, בית הלל
Beit Hillel is more מיקל, meikel, is more than a רביעית. revi'it.
But one cheek is less than a רביעית. revi'it. So בית שמאי—בית
הלל is being strict, like בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you don't
transgress until a רביעית revi'it and בית הלל Beit Hillel says even
one cheek, which where—if it's one cheek, one cheek is less than
a רביעית, revi'it, says the גמרא. Gemara So גמרא Gemara, says אמר
ליה, amar leih, he said back to him, no, פיטשיל באוג מלך
הבשן פיטשיל. pitschil be-Og Melech HaBashan pitschil. That's a great line. The
גמרא, Gemara you know, it assumes—it has a sense of humor. The
גמרא Gemara is implicitly assuming that as opposed to the idea of
a כותבת, right, which is described by something outside of you, מלא
לוגמיו mlo lugmav is described by your, your cheek, possessive, and that
each person it would be different. And that what—of course since when
do you have a שיעור shiur that changes by the person? Ah,
you would have said—you could have said an—well, but say the same
by food. No, by food it's an objective amount no matter how
big the
person. Right, normally we go by averages even exactly, things that measure
something on a person, an אמה ammah טבח tevach we go by
an average. By the food of יום כיפור we go by a
universal, I should say, which is a כותבת. Here the גמרא Gemara
is assuming we go by your particular size of your body, size
of your cheeks. So if that's true, so then sometimes the fill
of a cheek could be bigger than a רביעית revi'it if you're
really big guy, as the גמרא Gemara describes by saying עוג מלך
הבשן. Og Melech HaBashan. Okay, but if you're a big guy, you
got big cheeks, for you בית הלל Beit Hillel would be a
קולא. kula. So the reason it wasn't said בית הלל Beit Hillel
is a חומרא chumra is because we were thinking about a big
guy, which is a funny point because normally we think about an
average guy. Which by the way, this is very important. This means
because what is מלא לוגמיו mlo lugmav on יום כיפור, you know,
and it's important when there's circumstances that you tell somebody, okay, you
can drink but do it בשיעורים, be-shiurim, you know, do less than
the minimum amount and, you know, spread it out so that the
separate minimums don't combine. So how much do we assume is the
minimum for drinking? According to this גמרא Gemara comes out that at
least the average is less than a רביעית revi'it because it assumed
מלא לוגמיו mlo lugmav was less than a רביעית revi'it unless we
were talking about a big guy.
Okay, this is saying that that when בית הלל Beit Hillel made
a statement he was thinking about עוג. Og.
Exactly, he was thinking about a big guy, let's put it that
way. והוה ליה בית שמאי לחומרא. ve-hava leih Beit Shammai le-chumra. And
with a big guy בית שמאי Beit Shammai is more מחמיר. machmir.
Okay, so now we get to this question. Now the גמרא Gemara
sort of wakes up and realizes what? Really? The מלא לוגמיו mlo
lugmav is you specifically? When do we say that, that a שיעור
shi'ur is about you specifically and not about some universal? So מתקיף
לה רב זירא. matkif lah Rav Zeira. So רב זירא Rav Zeira
asks, מה
ישנא
אכילה דכל חד וחד בכותבת?
mah yishna achilah
de-chol chad ve-chad be-kotevet?
Why by eating on יום כיפור everybody is measured by the same
size of the date? ומה ישנא שתייה דכל חד וחד בדידיה? u-mah
yishna shtiyah de-chol chad ve-chad be-dideih? And why is it by drinking
you've now implicitly said that we go by each person's own personal,
own personal, you know, size? So how come it changes? אמר ליה
אביי, amar leih Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, אקימו ליה רבנן דבכותבת
בהכי מיתבא דעתיה. akimu leih rabanan de-be-kotevet be-hachi mitva dateih. The rabbis
established that the size of a date and
that much will sort of put your mind at ease, meaning will
somewhat abate your sense of affliction. בציר מהכי לא מיתבא, batziar me-hachi
lo mitva,
less than that not, regardless of size, that's a universal, that that
will impact your state. בשתייה בדידיה מיתבא דעתיה בדחבריה לא. bi-shtiyah be-dideih
mitva dateih be-de-chavreih lo.
By drinking only a size proportional to you will lead to a
יישוב הדעת yishuv ha-da'at and an abating of the affliction, but if
it's the size of your friend's cheeks, that won't. So somehow his
answer is: the rabbis know. They know that
when it comes to eating, that the same minimum amount will have
the same impact, not satiating, but it'll abate the affliction, it'll have
an impact, you know, equal regardless of size, whereas drinking, it depends
on the size of the person. So אמר ליה, amar leih, סומכוס
בככותבת, Sumchos be-khakotevet, ובהכי מיתבא
דעתיה. ve-hachi meitva da'ateih. מתיב רב זירא, mativ Rav Zeira, רב זירא
Rav Zeira is not happy. He's the same מקשה makshan from the
beginning. וכולם ככותבת ve-khulam ke-khakotevet ועוג מלך הבשן ככותבת? ve-Og Melech Ha-Bashan
ke-khakotevet? So you started to talk about Og, so let's talk about
Og. You mean to tell me you've got Og, you've got this
twenty-foot guy, and him a little date is going to help the
same way it helps a normal guy? אמר ליה אביי, amar leih
Abaye, so אביי Abaye is not perturbed, he is not backing down.
קים להו לרבנן, kim lehu le-rabbanan, the rabbis established, דבהכי מיתבא דעתיה,
de-vaha'chi meitva da'ateih, yes, that amount causes an abatement of the affliction.
ובציר מהכי לא מיתבא דעתיה, u-vatzir mei-hachi lo meitva da'ateih, less than
that not. מיהו, mihu, nevertheless, here's how I answer your Og question.
כולי עלמא טובא, kulei alma tuva, most people you eat that minimum
amount, it achieves a good deal of abating the affliction. עוג מלך
הבשן פורתא, Og Melech Ha-Bashan purta, עוג מלך הבשן Og Melech Ha-Bashan
achieves it but only in a little bit. A little bit makes
me feel better, less than that wouldn't have made me feel better
at all. With that, I feel a tiny bit better. Other people,
less than that wouldn't have made them feel better at all, with
that amount, makes them feel a good deal better. Now maybe it's
a little bit like Michael says, that eating is very psychological, I
think drinking is also
psychological, but somehow you got something of a substantial size, that impacts
the way that it feels, but I know if you're עוג מלך
הבשן, Og Melech Ha-Bashan, I don't know if that's a substantial
size. Anyway, he's saying that there's a threshold, below the threshold doesn't
do it for anybody, above the threshold does it for everybody but
to a different degree. That's אביי's Abaye's answer. We're not done. מתיב
ליה רב
זירא, mativ leih Rav Zeira, רב זירא Rav Zeira is still not
happy, he challenged him. בשר שמן בככותבת basar shamen be-khakotevet ולולבי גפנים
בככותבת? ve-lulavei gefanim be-khakotevet? How about the type of food you're eating?
You got some nice fatty steak the size of a date and
you got grape leaves the size of a date, you're telling me
it should be the same size? Now, the point is that had
nothing to do with the idea of מלא לוגמיו, melo lugmav, he
could have asked that about when the משנה mishna that says all
food is בככותבת. be-khakotevet. But presumably, if it was just the משנה,
mishna, he would have said, look, I get the idea that you
need to have universal minimums
and we're not going to look at the specific details, how big
you are, how small you are, whatever. The whole idea is you
have a standard, a standard applies to all people, all food. But
as soon as you are, there's a kink in the armor, as
soon as you're saying that it really, we're not looking at universals,
it really matters in every case how it affects the person and
מלא לוגמיו melo lugmav is going to vary from person to person,
then you've destroyed the whole system. Then how do you ever have
a universal? And anyway, it should matter what type of food you
eat. Very good
question. So let's see his answer. אמר ליה אביי, amar leih Abaye,
so you know what's coming. אביי Abaye says, קים להו לרבנן, kim
lehu le-rabbanan, yes, the rabbis established, דבהכי מיתבא דעתיה, de-vaha'chi meitva da'ateih,
there's a threshold. That amount, no matter what the food is, with
that amount you, it causes an abatement of the affliction, less than
that nothing, that amount yes. ובציר מהכי לא מיתבא דעתיה, u-vatzir mei-hachi
lo meitva da'ateih, less than that threshold does absolutely nothing regardless of
the food. מיהו, mihu, once you hit the threshold, בשר שמן טובא,
basar shamen tuva, if you're eating good fatty meat, that does a
lot, ולולבי גפנים פורתא, ve-lulavei gefanim purta, and grape leaves very little.
So basically, אביי's Abaye's answer is, which is, yeah, it is true
about this, this minimum is true for every person. It's just that
this is what the rabbis know in terms of how that, that
this happens to be universal, happens to be true for every person.
Whereas by drinking, there's a different by each person. מתיב ליה רבא,
mativ leih Rava, so רבא Rava asked. Okay, so that's the end
of that discussion. It's really quite a, I mean we're going to
have a related point in a minute. But the point is, this
is really a fascinating thing, right? When else do we have that
by a שיעור shi'ur you go and by each individual? The whole
idea of a שיעור shiur. is a universal. And as soon as
you, now if you would have said just הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai, fine, that would have ended the conversation. But if you're
going to say the idea of going by a different size for
drinking by each individual is because of how it impacts the individual,
then you understand what רב זירא's Rav Zeira's questions and how do
we ever have these standards and minimums? We should always say that
by each individual, it won't have the same effect if you're big,
if you're small, what you're eating, and so on. And the answer
of אביי, Abaye, you can decide, does not seem to be fully
satisfying, not to make a pun. Yes.
I actually see this as a hugely important מחלוקת. machlokes. In other
words, אביי Abaye is constantly coming back and saying that the nature
and authentic meaning of religious experience has to have an essentially subjective
dimension to it within an objectified framework. And that type of subjectivity
is completely contiguous with the nature of the מצוה mitzvah and the
experience. Aha. And רב זירא Rav Zeira is saying no, you have
to have objective standards, standards, we hear this discourse all the time,
right, standards, everyone's got to measure up in the exact same way
against the standard.
I think there's something to that. So thank you, that's a very
good point, meaning meaning אביי's Abaye assumption that that, I mean, which
is sort of, you know, which is it's anchored in the statement
about the מלא לוגמיו, melo lugmav, but his assumption that yes it
does actually work for every individual is a very powerful assumption. But
he has to do a lot more work in bridging the gap
between that assumption and the reality of objective standards. So that's why,
right, his closing of the gap is harder to buy into, but
the assumption he's working with is a very powerful one. So I
appreciate that, that's a very good point. Yes.
Do you think קים להו לרבנן kim lehu lerabanan is the rabbis
established or the rabbis knew?
I think it means more they knew. Yeah. I think it means
that context means like they, you know, they knew. But it's an
by the way that is a good point though. The קים להו
לרבנן kim lehu lerabanan as opposed to our whole assertion before about
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai and not allowing it to be
אושניא בן קנז, Oshnaya ben Kenaz, right, קים להו לרבנן kim lehu
lerabanan suggests that the rabbis, you know, evaluated something and established and
determined. How about the גמרא Gemara even earlier when it says אוכל
אשר יאכל ochel asher ye'achel and it says and the rabbis established,
you know, שיעור חמין שאין בית הבליעה מחזקת, shiur chamin she'ein beis
hablia machzekes, which shows a rabbinic input into determining what those sizes
are, which then raises the questions about the גמרא's Gemara resistance by
עתניאל בן קנז. Osniel ben Kenaz.
Yes. I mean, you do have some subjective שיעורים, like the חפינה,
chafina, right?
I don't think that whatever that's more of an act of חפינה
chafina and whatever, I don't think that that's that's as relevant to
the universal issues as this. Okay, yeah.
What about sitting in a סוכה, sukkah, is the size of you
subjective?
Yeah, that, no, we don't go. We say ראשו ורובו, rosho v'rubo,
but we define that, well the act of sitting again, if you
say you gotta put your body in that's not a שיעור. shiur
שיעור shiur, is something that translates into, you know, a quantity, a
minimum amount that can be measured, not the act. You have to
get your whole body into the water of a מקוה, mikvah, that's
not a שיעור, shiur but the שיעור is how much water do
you need. So the size of a סוכה sukkah to fit ראשו
ורובו rosho v'rubo of a person is an average person, is not
each person individually. Okay, let's go, now the גמרא's Gemara gonna have
a similar questions about being things being consistent. מתיב ליה רבא, Masiv
lei Rava, so רבא Rava asks,
כזית is the גירסא girsa let's say, כזית בכדי אכילת פרס, kezayis
b'chdei achilas pras, did I skip a line? Okay, חצי פרס בכדי
אכילת פרס. chatzi pras b'chdei achilas pras. So רבא Rava says I
don't get it, or some actually have a or some have a
גירסא girsa of כזית בכדי אכילת פרס וככותבת בכדי אכילת פרס, kezayis
b'chdei achilas pras v'chekosaves b'chdei achilas pras, meaning, no, I'm sorry, I
did skip a line. Going back to right, I there's another רבא
Rava that's just like it. מתיב ליה רבא, Masiv lei Rava, כזית
בכדי אכילת פרס וככותבת בכדי אכילת פרס? kezayis b'chdei achilas pras v'chekosaves
b'chdei achilas pras? רבא Rava says I don't get it. Right, when
you have foods that you that you combine in act of eating
by a forbidden food, eating a כזית over the time it takes
to eat half a loaf of bread, which is basically about eight
or nine ביצים. beitzim. It's the it's one it's one meal's worth.
Okay, which we usually say is a five minutes, some people say
more, nine minutes, whatever. Anyway, that when the minimum amount is the
כזית we say if you eat it within that period of time,
אכילת פרס, achilas pras, eight or nine minutes, it's like one act
of eating. How can we use the same minimum amount of time
when we're dealing with יום כיפור and a ככותבת, k'kotevet which is
a date, right, which is like twice as big, maybe that should
combine over twice as long of a time. Why does it also
only combine within nine minutes, which is a very important קולא, kula,
right, which means that if you have to eat on יום כיפור
little by little, then you go by you know after whatever five
minutes, nine minutes you can eat again. So why is it the
same amount of time, it's a bigger size it should be more
time that it combines. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so
אביי Abaye backs his answer, קים להו לרבנן, kim lehu lerabanan, the
rabbis have it as a you know know it, דהכי מיתבא דעתיה
ובהכי לא מיתבא דעתיה, d'hachi misva daiteih ub'hachi lo misva daiteih, eating
done within that period of time of אכילת פרס achilas pras causes
you to settle your mind, abates the affliction, more than that does
not even though you're eating more than a כזית. So an act
of אכילה achila is defined by that amount of time, and achieving
an abating of the עינוי inuiv is achieved in the same amount
of time, the rabbis know it. מתיב ליה רבא, Masiv lei Rava,
so רבא Rava asks again, כזית or ככותבת בכדי אכילת פרס חצי
פרס בכדי אכילת פרס, kekosaves b'chdei achilas pras chatzi pras b'chdei achilas
pras,
there's another time we take אכילת פרס. achilas pras. If you eat
טמא tamei food, it makes you טמא. tamei. Now normally טמא tamei
food cannot make a person טמא. tamei. Okay, טמא tamei food can
only make like קדשים kodshim טמא. tamei. But according to the rabbis,
if you eat a half of a loaf worth of טמא tamei
food and you put it in your body, it will make you
טמא. tamei. Eat a half of a loaf over how much time?
Over the time of eating a half a loaf of a בכדי
אכילת פרס. b'chdei achilas pras. Okay, so I'm sorry, that's a half
of a, it's a חצי פרס, chatzi pras, half of a half.
Okay, but so but that is crazy, right?
So let me just finish.
If you eat
basically, okay, you've got your loaf which
is your loaf of bread. Half of it, half of a loaf
is a פרס, pras, פרס pras is a half. Okay, that's one
meal's worth. Okay, meal's worth is a פרס, pras, okay? It's about
eight to nine ביצים. beitzim. Okay? So how long does that take?
I don't know, let's say five minutes, something more, let's say five
minutes to eat that. So when you eat a כזית, okay, for
let's say, you know, חזיר chazir or נבלה, neveila, okay, if you
eat the כזית over אכילת פרס, achilat pras, the time it takes
to eat eight of them or nine of them, it combines. When
you eat a
ככותבת on יום כיפור, right? Right? Which we said is about the
size of a ביצה, who knows, let's call it roughly two to
three כזיתים. kezaitim. Okay, that's by יום כיפור also if you eat
it within five minutes, but if you eat you should be given
more time to eat it to transgress. Doesn't matter. How about a
half of a פרס, pras, okay, חצי פרס? chatzi pras? Okay, so
half of a half of a loaf which is basically let's call
it four זיתים. zeitim. Okay? Now if that's טמא tamei and you
ingest that, okay, then you become טמא. tamei Also the time it
takes to eat the full
פרס, pras, okay, the same five minutes. How come that is? Okay,
so let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
It should be two and a half minutes, right?
Exactly, yeah. Exactly, this should be half the time and this should
be a quarter of the time and it's all the same amount
of time. So אמר ליה רב פפא, amar lei Rav Pappa, so
said רב פפא, Rav Pappa, הנך לטומאת גויה דלאו דאורייתא היא. hanach
l'tumat geviyah d'lav d'Oraita hi.
Forget about making your body טמא tamei by eating. That's not a
biblical idea, so we can say what we want. מי אמר רב
פפא הכי? mi amar Rav Pappa hachi? Does רב פפא Rav Pappa
really say that? והכתיב, ve-hachtiv, doesn't the verse say, ולא תטמאו בהם
ונטמתם בם? ve-lo titamu bahem ve-nitmetem bam? You shall not become טמא
tamei by them and you will make yourself טמא tamei through them.
Now that טומאה means eating non-kosher food, but we're going to read
that as a literal טומאה. ואמר רב פפא, ve-amar Rav Pappa, מכאן
שטומאת גויה דאורייתא היא. mikan she-tumat geviyah d'Oraita hi. Here you see
when you eat טמא things you become טמא and it's biblical. So
we still have to explain why the same amount of time. So,
לא מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא. la mi-derabbanan ve-k'ra asmakhta b'alma. Even when
he says דאורייתא d'Oraita he doesn't mean דאורייתא. d'Oraita. He really means
it's מדרבנן mi-derabbanan and he's using the פסוק as a support. Okay,
so we can give it the same amount of time and be
lenient and say anything more than that five minutes you're off the
hook because it's all מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan. By the way, it's also very
nice bracketing the issues we started with. What's דאורייתא? d'Oraita? What's מדרבנן?
mi-derabbanan? The rabbis, are they defining the שיעורים? How much is that
straight הלכה למשה מסיני? Halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai? How much, you know, at
one point the גמרא Gemara resisted the idea that the rabbis defined
it, at another point it says no, the rabbis established this is
how much you can swallow, the rabbis established that this is אכילה
achila or no, that this is what causes ישוב הדעת. yishuv hadaat.
So how much do the rabbis define those parameters? Similar I thought,
how much are the rabbis defining the parameters of the ענויים? inuyim?
And the גמרא ends with a discussion of something that's claimed to
be a דאורייתא, d'Oraita, even the phrase דאורייתא d'Oraita is being used,
and it says it doesn't really mean it, it's really מדרבנן. mi-derabbanan.
So that interplay of דאורייתא, d'Oraita, מדרבנן mi-derabbanan and rabbinic interpretation and
by the way, the whole issue about changing the amount of the
כזיתים kezaitim once the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is built, right, and
the role of rabbinic interpretation affecting דאורייתא d'Oraita is a very interesting
consistent theme throughout these issues. Maybe we'll continue here tomorrow.